Arlington Heights, Ill. Congregational United Church of Christ records, 1959-2024.
Congregational Library & Archives
Arlington Heights, Ill. Congregational United Church of Christ records, 1959-2024.
RG5587
Congregational Library & Archives
1.09 Cubic Feet
(1 box)
The Congregational Church of Arlington Heights, Illinois, was gathered in 1959. The church was seeded, initially, by the Church Extension Committee of the Illinois Conference of the United Church of Christ. Construction of the church's sole building was completed in 1963. In 1964, the name of the church was changed to the Congregational United Church of Christ. Throughout the church's history, the church was focused on mission work. The church underwent a restructuring process starting in 1998 that was completed in 2000. The church became Open and Affirming in the early 2000s. The church closed in 2024. The collection contains both administrative records and vital membership records and includes a church register and an accompanying index, constitutions, building legal records, membership lists, baptismal records, and marriage records.
Congregational United Church of Christ (Arlington Heights, Ill.)
Congregational Church of Arlington Heights (Ill.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Illinois Conference of the United Church of Christ in December 2024; accession number 2024-46.
Custodial History
Materials in this collection were given to the Illinois Conference of the United Church of Christ in 2024 following the closure of the church. This information is documented on a piece of correspondence that is stored within the collection's accession folder.
Historical Note
The Congregational Church of Arlington Heights, Illinois, was gathered in 1959 with Rev. W. Rowland Koch serving as the first minister. The church was seeded, initially, by the Church Extension Committee of the Illinois Conference of the United Church of Christ. Koch moved to Arlington Heights in January of 1959 and began work to gather a church. A steering committee was formed in April and the first service for the church was held on May 3, 1959. Worship was originally held at the Pioneer Park Fieldhouse and then at the South Junior High School until September of 1963 when construction on a church building was completed. In 1964 the name of the church was changed to Congregational United Church of Christ.
During Rev. Koch's pastorate, the church became very involved in mission-based work with the formation of the Missions and Stewardship, Social Action, Women's Fellowship, and Pilgrim Fellowship committees. Some of the mission work included the sponsoring of a Cuban refugee family and the Vietnamese Boat People, the Pleasant Valley Farm venture, and Casa Central in Chicago. Rev. Koch served alone until 1980 when Rev. Nan Conser was hired as an associate pastor. Rev. Koch pulled back from pastoral duties in 1985 due to illness and both he and Rev. Conser retired from the church in 1987.
They were succeeded by Rev. Howard Bowman in 1988. His pastorate ended in 1997 and he followed by Pastor Jeffrey Phillips, an openly gay clergyman. During his short tenure at the church, Pastor Jeffrey proposed a restructuring of the church from committees into Ministry teams. That work was taken up by the Revisioning Committee. In 1999, Rev. David Russel became the minister of the church and the work of the Revisioning Committee was completed in 2000.
The 2000s saw the church's mission work focus on the local community. The church's back property was converted into a community garden and the church held frequent choir concerts open to all. The church also took on the Open and Affirming status in the early 2000s. The church continued to serve the Arlington Heights community until 2024 when it dissolved.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains both administrative records and vital membership records for the Congregational United Church of Christ in Arlington Heights, Illinois. The collection includes a church register and an accompanying index, worship bulletins and programs for special events, constitutions, policy documents, building legal records, membership lists, baptismal records, transfer certificates, and marriage records.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into the two series listed below. Materials within each series have been arranged first by chronological order, by start date, and then by groupings of continuous materials.
Series 1: Administrative records, 1959-2024
Series 2: Membership records, 1959-2023
Baptismal records.; Church buildings.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Marriage records.; Necrologies.; Arlington Heights (Ill.) -- Church history.; Congregational Church of Arlington Heights (Ill.); Congregational United Church of Christ (Arlington Heights, Ill.)
- Administrative records, 1959 2024; 1959-2024; 12 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records related to the administration of the Congregational United Church of Christ of Arlington Heights, Illinois. The series also contains programs and bulletins for special services and events in the church's history. This series includes constitutions, policy documents, histories, anniversary-related documents, committee reports, and legal records related to the church building.
  - Special programs and worship bulletins, 1959 2022; 1959-2022 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Church structure, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Histories, 1960 2008; 1960-2008 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - First annual meeting, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Constitutions, 1960 1964; 1960, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Policies, 1962 1991; 1962, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Building legal records, 1963 2022; 1963-2022 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous administrative records, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fact finding committee report, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 25th anniversary records, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Final worship service programs, 2024 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Church exterior architectural image, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Membership records, 1959 2023; 1959-2023; 1 Volume; 17 Folders
  This series contains records related to the membership of the Congregational United Church of Christ in Arlington Heights, Illinois. The series includes baptismal records, marriage records, transfer records and certificates, membership lists and related records, and the church's register as well as a 2004 index for the register compiled by church members.
  - Church register, 1959 2024; 1959-2024 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Charter members, 1959 1960; 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Book of the covenant, 1959 1999; 1959-1999 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Book of the covenant, 1999 2020; 1999-2020 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Child baptism records, 1959 1972; 1959-1972 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Adult baptism records, 1959 1981; 1959-1981 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Membership certificates, 1959 1963; 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Membership certificates, 1963 1969; 1963-1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Membership certificates, 1969 1977; 1969-1977 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Membership certificates, 1977 1986; 1977-1986 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Marriage records, 1967 1997; 1967-1997 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Transfer certificates, 1975 1980; 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Rosemary Ann Kimpel seminary recommendation, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Index of records, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Transfers from church, 2004 2023; 2004-2023 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Transfers to church, 2006 2019; 2006-2019 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Membership list labels, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Non-member vital records, 2009 2018; 2009-2018 (Box 1, Folder 28)